Matthew Gooch

Solutions Architect, Business Analyst and Project Manager



matthew.w.gooch@outlook.com

in linkedin.com/in/matthew-gooch-5502b745/



Key skills

- Enterprise Architecture
- Systems and Business Analysis
- SQL and RDBMS Modelling
- Multi-Dimensional Database Modelling
- Business Intelligence and Analytics
- Requirements Analysis
- User Story Creation
- Business Process Modelling
- Business Case Development
- Software Vendor Selection
- Procurement Processes
- Project Planning and Management
- Stakeholder Management
- Change Management

A career information solutions professional with over 25 years experience in analysing, developing, designing, managing and delivering benefit-centred solutions to clients predominantly in the utilities industry. Significant experience in waterfall and agile methods, as well as Prince2 environments.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Business Analyst

Pelican Business Services, Nailsea September 2019 – current date

Responsible for the analysis and design of data integrations between systems in a large transformation programme implementing a new billing platform using the MS Dynamics ERP platform :-

- Production of user stories and requirements documents using agile techniques
- Population of user stories in the MS DevOps system
- Management of system change in a cross-company environment

Enterprise Architect

Bristol Water, Bristol October 2018 – September 2019

Responsible for the establishment of an enterprise architecture capability within the organisation which included :-

- Review and selection of an enterprise architecture methodology (TOGAF)
- Extensive modification of TOGAF to be reflective of the company's architectural maturity levels and resources
- Definition of architecture standards and principles and how these should be applied to change programmes
- Definition of skillsets and roles required for the architecture capability
- Definition of benefits realisation metrics and measurement processes
- Management of the enterprise architecture software vendor procurement process
- Tutoring and mentorship of colleagues in enterprise architecture practices
- Establishment of an Architecture Governance Board responsible for approving organisational and system changes
- Defining roadmaps from baseline architectures, through transitional architectures and on to target architectures
- Management of stakeholders in understanding the impact of change

Solution Architect

Bristol Water, Bristol June 2018 – October 2018

Acted as a Solution Architect in a digital transformation programme for a mobile working solution:-

- Review of existing mobile solution and identification of gaps between AS-IS and TO-BE functionality
- Production of tender materials in collaboration with the Procurement team
- Extensive engagement in the vendor selection process

Lead Process Analyst

Bristol Water, Bristol January 2018 – June 2018

Responsible for company-wide process analysis to satisfy GDPR regulations :-

- Mapped over 200 business processes in Sparx Enterprise Architect capturing core data flow, systems usage and organisational activity
- Definition and deployment of GDPR data classifications against data objects to allow prioritisation of remedial activities
- Managed the activities of 3 other process analysts

Methodologies

- TOGAF
- BPMN
- Structured Analysis and Design

Professional Certifications

- TOGAF 9.2 Certified Practitioner
- ArchiMate 2.1 Certified

Software

- Sparx Enterprise Architect
- Mega EA software
- Avolution's Abacus EA software
- SAP ERP and CRM
- MS SQL Server Management Studio
- Oracle Database Tools
- MS Project
- All MS Office Software

Education

BA(Hons) Systems Analysis

Solution Architect Bristol Water, Bristol July 2017 – January 2018

Provided solution advice on changes to the company's implementation of systems and business processes:-

- Produced business and systems impact assessments of changes introduced by MOSL, the Open Water Market Operator
- Managed change with impacted business departments
- Designed system enhancements to reflect the new requirements
- Provided feasibility assessments and company responses to MOSL relating to their change proposals, in particular, a new digital communication strategy the MOSL Digital Strategy Committee was considering
- Implemented a new digital Live Chat capability allowing customers to contact operational support agents through a web chat interface
- Implemented a new document management system allowing remote access to ISO9000 quality controlled working policies, procedures and protocols

Project Manager

MOSL, London January 2017 – July 2017

Responsible for the project management and delivery of a new website for MOSL, the market operator for the UK Non-household Water Retail market :-

- Worked closely with the Chief Executive and reported to the IT Director, to understand their vision for a new company website to be used by both internal staff members and external water companies
- Managed a team of 5 internal staff responsible for production of material to populate the new content management system
- Managed the relationship with the main web company to ensure timely delivery of website capability in an agile manner
- Managed the relationship with external service providers needed to support the implementation of the new system
- Managed the relationship with third-party contractors developing data visualisation systems to ensure they delivered key geographical reporting capabilities accessible via the website
- Managed the deployment of the new website and ensured its accessibility by the external water companies through Azure single sign-on methods
- Conducted post-implementation reviews and produced a costed catalogue of future enhancements road-mapped into functionally related deliverables

Lead Solution Architect

Bristol Water, Bristol June 2015 – January 2017

Held prime responsibility for the design and delivery of system and organisational change relating to the Government's regulatory introduction of the world's largest water retail market:

- Acted as Bristol Water's sole representative at national industry meetings to design the new water retail market operational and governance methods
- Analysed the resultant market code requirements for the impact on Bristol Water's business and systems architecture
- Designed appropriate organisational changes within the constraints of the company's Target Operating Model
- Performed detailed process analysis of operational requirements and designed a streamlined, consistent, business process supported by a new workflow system and externally-facing service portal, before implementing these into a completely new business function
- Designed changes to existing systems architecture and corresponding financial elements in the company's SAP ERP and FICO systems and mobile works management systems
- Integrated internal systems with third-party communications systems to provide electronic transactions interfaced with the central systems run by the market operator
- Played a central role in the assurance process run by PA Consulting resulting in the successful achievement of the Market Entry Assurance certification

Lead Solution Architect Bristol Water, Bristol January 2012 – June 2015

Lead Architect and Analyst on a variety of Bristol Water projects :-

- Ran the selection process for an external solution provider for a major SAP CRM upgrade and enhancement programme
- Implementation of a new human resources system
- Introduction of new enterprise architecture software and acted in the role of the Design Authority for use of that software
- Detailed requirements analysis and software vendor selection for a Laboratory Management system
- Conducted a substantial analysis of internal business functions and their operation, resulting in a report of detailed recommendations for improvements and organisational change
- Executed a review of administrative activities within the company and presented a report of recommendations to the Chief Executive
- Analysis, design and delivery of workflow capabilities supporting hazard reporting obligations

Business Systems Analyst

eDF Energy, Gloucester November 2010 – December 2011

Systems Analyst working with a multi-disciplinary team on the Voyager transformation programme :-

- Analysis of Data Warehouse and Business Intelligence requirements for an £80m business transformation project
- Detailed requirements elicitation across a range of stakeholders, from both a business and technical arena
- Responsibility for Data Architecture design and documentation using the MEGA CASE tool
- Developed working practices for the use of the MEGA tool within a Data Warehouse project and environment
- Analysed and documented enterprise architecture components using MEGA
- Participated in internal forums to expand the best practices of using the MEGA toolset within the company

Business Systems Analyst

E.ON Energy Services, Kingswinford March 1999 – May 2010

Systems Analyst working on a large number of projects, both commercially generated and driven through regulatory changes including:-

- Business Intelligence and Management Information System development
- Responsible for the full SDLC of various projects
- Analysed and designed new systems to communicate data through the Data Transfer Catalogue, Nexus and Proteus protocols
- Designed the system to handle the data migration of 2 million customers from a mainframe based Non-Half Hourly Data Collection systems to an Oraclebased SRLDP NHHDC system

Other Roles

- Analyst for Hyder (SWALEC) on the 1998 deregulated electricity market
- Analyst for Lloyds TSB on the Year 2000 impact on their HOLOS OLAP toolset
- Senior consultant at an independent business intelligence and MIS consultancy
- Consultant at two software houses specialising in OLAP, business intelligence and Executive Information Systems